Guide to the New York Times Company records. Arthur Hays Sulzberger papers
New York Public Library
- Series II. Subjects, 1823, 1858, 1875, 1891, 1895, 1900-1910, 1916-1972, 1978-1999, n.d; 210.75 boxes, 9 volumes
  - Military Forces (United States)
    - General
      These folders contain letters, memoranda, and other documents about AHS's views and the NYT's reports and editorials on military matters, AHS's visits to military installations and defense plants, speeches to military schools, attendance at conferences on diverse aspects of the defense program, visits of military officers to the NYT, and related matters. A recurrent theme is the need to inform troops about current affairs, especially the reasons for military action and the need for peacetime defenses. In 1941 AHS assigned Hilton H. Railey to conduct a survery of morale in Army camps. The survey was not published in the NYT but was sent to the pertinent Cabinet officers. This survey was instrumental in the creation of the Army Information and Education School and many documents in these folders concern the survey and other aspects of the information and education program. Also included here are AHS's speech to the Air War College on "Public Opinion in the Modern State" (1956), correspondence about AHS's visit to Fort Myer, Va., the Defense Department, and other installations in the Washington, D.C. area (1955), the possible closing of the Army Information and Education School at Ft. Slocum (1953-1954), B. Fine's survey of military information programs (1951), the unification of the armed services, which AHS favored (1945-1947, 1950, 1951), AHS's participation in a special meeting of the Personnel Policy Board (1949), a Defense Orientation Conference attended by AHS (1948), correspondence with Vannevar Bush about military research and problem of national security vs. press responsibility to report developments, correspondence prompted by Hanson Baldwin's report on military developments that allegedly breached security and related memoranda (1947-1948), correspondence about an Air War College seminar for civilians attended by AHS and subsequent trip to Eglin Field, Florida (1947), correspondence about AHS's service on a citizens committee for universal military training, pamphlets and reports from this committee, and his speech to NYC teachers and school administrators advocating Universal Military Training and Universal Military Service, and letters about the speech (1943-1945), a letter to Secretary of the Nave James Forrestal, after AHS's tour of Red Cross installations, criticizing the Navy's attitude toward the Red Cross and cooperation with other services (1944), correspondence about AHS's participation in a tour of military bases in the South by newspaper editors and publishers (1944), correspondence about the War Department's documentary and education films (1943-1944), AHS's trip to Western defense plants, Railey's report on the possibility of sabotage (1942), memoranda about Railey's survey of Army morale (1941), and a memorandum of issues to be discussed at a special editorial conference on national defense (1938).
      - 1948-1968, 1979-1980 (Box 204, Folder 8-15)
      - 1938-1947 (Box 205, Folder 1-7)
    - Army Morale Survey (The Railey Report)
      In 1941 AHS assigned Hilton H. Railey to conduct a survery of morale in Army camps. The survey was not published in the NYT but was sent to the pertinent Cabinet officers. This survey was instrumental in the creation of the Army Information and Education School.
      - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 205, Folder 8)
      - Mr. Sulzberger Pt. I, 1941 (Box 205, Folder 9)
      - Mr. Sulzberger Pt. II, 1941 (Box 206, Folder 1)
      - Mr. Sulzberger Documentation, 1941 (Box 206, Folder 2)
      - Supplement, 1941 (Box 206, Folder 3)
  - Military Service by AHS
    - General, 1917-1967 (Box 206, Folder 4-5)
      Includes correspondence about reunions of AHS's unit (322nd Field Artillery Regiment), his financial contributions, meeting with its commanding officer, A. B. Warfield, booklets and newsletters, correspondence with fellow veterans, AHS's note of recollections about entering military service and wartime experiences (1962), AHS's letters to AOS relating some of his experiences (1951), a report on the 322nd Field Artillery's action at the front for Sept.-Oct. 1918 (undated), Louis Johnson's letter about obtaining AHS's appointment as a lieutenant colonel in the Reserves, with a memorandum about his eligibility (1939 or 1940), records relating to AHS's discharge from the Army (1917-1921), and photographs of groups of soldiers including AHS.
    - Scrapbook, 1917-1918 (Box 281)
      Contains service documents and photographs.
  - Millington Publications, Ltd., 1951 (Box 206, Folder 6)
  - Milwaukee Journal, 1935, 1952-1961 (Box 206, Folder 7)
  - Miniature Edition, 1933 (Box 206, Folder 8)
  - Minifon, 1954-1955 (Box 206, Folder 9)
  - Minneapolis Star & Tribune, 1939-1956 (Box 206, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Letters and Papers
    These five folders contain diverse letters, memoranda, and other papers that have no connection with specific subjects but that are of biographical interest or shed light on AHS's personality. The first folder contains memoranda to family members and NYT's associates, ranging from stories evidently intended for children to notes about personal or business relationships. Included are his contemplative reminiscences of 1958-1959, his note to OED comparing their relationship to AHS's with ASO (1959) and his letter to Morris S. Lazaron on the need for compromises (1945). The second folder contains official papers including AHS's birth certificate, grade school report card, military identification cards, driver's license, etc. The third folder contains correspondence, mainly about unusual requests or suggestions but includes letters by AHS's boyhood acquaintances and by some writers who could not be identified. Some of the letters ask about his aspirations, others about the causes of his success. The fourth and fifth folders contain Lucille Sunshine's collection of excerpts from AHS's articles, letters and speeches.
    - General, 1891-1968 (Box 206, Folder 11-13)
    - Excerpts from AHS's articles, speeches, letters, undated (Box 207, Folder 1-2)
    - Scrapbook, 1927-1940, n.d. (Box 285)
  - Missouri, University of
    - General, 1930, 1935, 1950-1959 (Box 207, Folder 3-5)
    - Award to AHS, 1958 (Box 291, Folder 7)
  - Mizpah Congregation (Chattanooga), 1925-1966 (Box 207, Folder 6-10)
    Includes correspondence with Rabbi Abraham Feinstein and others (1950-1966), correspondence and memoranda about the transfer to adjacent property from the Ochs Estate to the Congregation (1947-1948), AHS's address to the Temple Brotherhood on the Congregation's 80th anniversary, the history of the Congregation and role of Ochs family (1946), a photograph of the memorial to ASO, correspondence about the Congregation's financial problems and payments by Ochs Estate, including bequests under ASO's will (1935-1956), and correspondence with MBO, Henry B. Herts and others about the Julius and Bertha Ochs Memorial Temple, with cost estimates, drawings and other documents.
  - Mizrachi Women's Organization of America, 1958 (Box 208, Folder 1)
  - Montego Bay
  - Moore, C. J., Inc.
  - Monterey Californian, 1946 (Box 208, Folder 2)
  - Monticello, Virginia
  - Montmorency Paper Co., 1946-1967 (Box 208, Folder 3-4)
  - Montreal Gazette, 1935-1960 (Box 208, Folder 5-6)
  - Montreal Star, 1955-1958 (Box 208, Folder 7)
  - Moral Re-Armament, 1953-1958 (Box 208, Folder 8)
  - Morgan, J. P., & Co., 1951-1959 (Box 208, Folder 9)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1960-1961 (Box 208, Folder 10)
  - Morgan, Pierpont, Library
  - Morgue, 1947-1955 (Box 208, Folder 11)
    Includes letters and memoranda about the use of the morgue, OED's note calling the morgue "uninsurable because it is irreplaceable" (1955), Chester M. Lewis' memorandum about microfilming clipping files (1948), and a letter asking that obsolete derogatory material about the writer be removed from the files, with AHS's reply, refusing equest and explaining policy (1947).
  - Morningside Heights, Inc.
  - Morningstar Research Center, 1959 (Box 208, Folder 12)
  - Morris Plan Bank of Chattanooga
  - Moscow Bureau, 1934-1959 (Box 208, Folder 13-16)
    Includes memoranda and cables about staffing, coping with Russian censorship and visa requirements, supplying bureau staff during World War II, the cost of maintaining the bureau, and the possibility of closing it during the postwar era.
  - Mosquitoes
  - Mother's Day, 1934 (Box 208, Folder 17)
  - Motion Pictures
    Includes letters, memoranda, clippings, and other material about movie reviews by Bosley Crowther and other NYT critics and about NYT articles on the movie industry. Includes correspondence about Jack Gould's series on the effect of television on movie theaters (1951-1952), memoranda about the Fire Department of New York's action against the theater showing the controversial film, The Miracle (1951), correspondence about permission to use the NYT's name or a front page in films (1944-1946, 1952), correspondence with Will H. Hays about the portrayal of newspapers and reporters in films (1939) and about films considered immoral (1945), and correspondence with Howard Cullman and others about the listing of films for children (1936) and reviews of stage shows in movie theaters (1934).
    - 1952-1968 (Box 208, Folder 18-19)
    - 1934-1951 (Box 209, Folder 1-2)
  - Motogram Corporation
  - Mottoes and Maxims, 1929, 1948-1950 (Box 209, Folder 3)
  - Mount Holyoke College, 1952 (Box 209, Folder 4)
  - Mount Hope Cemetery
    - General, 1933-1966 (Box 209, Folder 5-11)
    - Blueprints, 1933-1937 (Box 293, Folder 9)
  - Mount Sinai Hospital
  - Muscular Dystrophy Association of America, 1955-1957 (Box 209, Folder 12)
  - Museum of the Recorded Word, 1931-1961 (Box 210, Folder 1-2)
  - Museums
  - Music, 1934-1965 (Box 210, Folder 3-4)
    Includes memoranda and letters about the NYT's reviews and critics, coverage of news of music and musicians, and related subjects, correspondence with Ira A. Hirschmann about music reviews, especially his criticism of the NYT's coverage of the Bayreuth Festival and of Wilhelm Furtwaengler's role in Nazi Germany and postwar visit to the U. S. (1936, 1945), a letter charging the NYT with bias against Furtwaengler, citing his obituary, Harold Schonberg's memorandum to AHS, and AHS's reply to the letter (1961), a letter praising Howard Taubman as the NYT's music editor (1942), letters about the replacement for Olin Downes as music critic, letters and memoranda about the choice of Taubman as music critic (1955-1956), memoranda by Taubman and Elliot Sanger replying to AHS's question about the survival of live music in the U. S. (1954), and correspondence between AHS and AOS about a plan to install Muzak in several departments (1960).
  - Music Art Center
  - Muzak
  - Nashville Banner, 1951-1958 (Box 210, Folder 5)
  - Natal Mercury, 1952 (Box 210, Folder 6)
  - The Nation, 1933-1956 (Box 210, Folder 7-10)
    The records in these folders concern criticism by The Nation of reports and/or editorials in the NYT and responses by the NYT. Among the issues are an editorial about criticism of Catholics in a NYT book review (1950), a Senate investigation of Alcoa (1941), an advertisement attacking Wendell Willkie (1940), reports on refugees in French camps, on pro-Fascist demonstrations in New York (1939), reports from Mexico and France (1938), memoranda and letters about a Samuel Silverman, who reportedly impersonated a NYT reporter and was suspected of channeling material to Freda Kirchwey on her acquisition of The Nation (1937), reports on the AFL-CIO split, correspondence with Leo Rosten about a series of charges by The Nation of omissions or distortions by the NYT, reports from China (1936), and reports on the banking and stock market crisis (1933).
  - The Nation (Rangoon, Burma), 1957-1958 (Box 210, Folder 11)
  - National Academy of Sciences
  - National Association for Mental Health, 1953-1955 (Box 210, Folder 12)
  - National Association of Book Publishers
  - National Association of Educational Broadcasters, 1954 (Box 210, Folder 13)
  - National Association of Engine and Boat Manufacturers, 1960 (Box 210, Folder 14)
  - National Association of Manufacturers, 1951 (Box 210, Folder 15)
  - National Book Fair, 1936-1937 (Box 210, Folder 16)
  - National Broadcasting Company, 1944-1965 (Box 210, Folder 17)
  - National Citizens Commission on International Cooperation
  - National Conference for Human Rights, 1958 (Box 210, Folder 18)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1932-1962 (Box 210, Folder 19)
  - National Conference of Editorial Writers, 1949-1966 (Box 211, Folder 1)
  - National Conference on Religion and Race, 1962 (Box 211, Folder 2)
  - National Conventions
  - National Council of Churches of Christ in the USA, 1952-1954 (Box 211, Folder 3)
  - National Council of Jewish Federations and Welfare Funds, 1934 (Box 211, Folder 4)
  - National Council on Crime and Delinquency, 1961 (Box 211, Folder 5)
  - National Council on the Arts and Government, 1957 (Box 211, Folder 6)
  - National Cyclopedia of American Biography, 1962 (Box 211, Folder 7)
  - National Dairy Products Corporation
  - National Economy League, 1932-1934 (Box 211, Folder 8)
  - National Edition, 1947-1966 (Box 211, Folder 9)
  - National Editorial Association, 1950 (Box 211, Folder 10)
  - National Federation of Independent Business, 1953-1966 (Box 211, Folder 11)
  - National Federation of Temple Brotherhoods, 1953 (Box 211, Folder 12)
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1933-1958 (Box 211, Folder 13)
  - National Health Council, 1952 (Box 211, Folder 14)
  - National Industrial Conference Board, 1956-1959 (Box 211, Folder 15)
  - National Institute of Social Sciences, 1941-1968 (Box 211, Folder 16)
  - National Jewish Hospital, 1935, 1957-1960 (Box 211, Folder 17)
  - National Labor Relations Board, 1936-1940 (Box 211, Folder 18)
  - National Observer
  - National Parks
  - National Planning Association, 1947, 1954-1957 (Box 211, Folder 19)
  - National Press Club, 1964-1965 (Box 211, Folder 20)
  - National Recovery Administration, 1933-1935 (Box 211, Folder 21-25)
  - National Refugee Service, 1939-1944 (Box 212, Folder 1)
  - National Religious Publicity Council, 1957 (Box 212, Folder 2)
  - National Retail Merchants Association
  - National Safety Council, 1942 (Box 212, Folder 3)
  - National Tuberculosis Association, 1938 (Box 212, Folder 4)
  - Nature Conservancy, 1960, 1965 (Box 212, Folder 5)
  - Naval Conference, 1935-1936 (Box 212, Folder 6)
  - Naval War College
  - Navy Relief Society, 1942-1943 (Box 212, Folder 7)
  - Nazism
    Correspondence about plans for memorial in Paris; AHS was asked to serve on a committee for the project but declined.-- Correspondence with J. Ofusa and members of his family, and with bureau members and others about the Ofusas, especially their visit to the U.S. in 1958; photos (1957-1967).-- A.M. Rosenthal's letter to AHS on his arrival in Tokyo; AHS's reply (1961).-- AHS's note welcoming W. Jorden to the staff (1952).-- Correspondence about Hugh Byas, Times's special correspondent in Tokyo (1928-1933).Correspondence about plans for memorial in Paris; AHS was asked to serve on a committee for the project but declined.
  - Near East College Association, 1953-1955 (Box 212, Folder 8)
  - Neediest Cases Campaign (Chattanooga)
  - Negroes, 1930-1968 (Box 212, Folder 9-13)
    Includes letters, memoranda, and other documents about the NYT's policy of covering the news of race relations and of identifying Negroes in news stories, especially news of crime, efforts of diverse organizations to improve race relations and AHS's role in these, the issue of capitalizing the word Negro, the employment of Negroes by the NYT, correspondence about the request by the Congress for Racial Equality that Claude Sitton testify on behalf of a civil rights demonstrator (1964), AHS's memorandum on his actions to desegregate the news in the Chattanooga Times (1957), AHS's letter (1952) and memorandum (1951) defining the NYT's policy on identifying persons in the news by race, letters and memoranda about identifying suspects in crime stories by race, especially Meyer Berger's memorandum on mugging, not published (1943), and AHS's report to Dwight D. Eisenhower on a race problem involving U. S. troops in Britain (1942).
  - Neiman-Marcus Company, 1948-1964 (Box 212, Folder 14)
  - Neo Gravure Printing Co., Inc., 1935-1959 (Box 212, Folder 15-16)
    Includes readers' mail about the NYT's testimony at a Senate committee hearing that during the 1948 trucking strike it made extra payments to Neo Gravure to assure the delivery of the Magazine and Book Review, AHS's replies and related memoranda (1959).
  - Netherland-America Foundation, 1955-1967 (Box 212, Folder 17)
  - Netherlands, 1943-1967 (Box 213, Folder 1)
  - New England Historic Genealogic Society, 1945 (Box 213, Folder 2)
  - New England Institute for Medical Research, 1956 (Box 213, Folder 3)
  - New England Women's Press Association, 1935 (Box 213, Folder 4)
  - New Orleans Times-Picayune, 1946, 1950 (Box 213, Folder 5)
  - New School for Social Research, 1951-1957 (Box 213, Folder 6)
  - The New Times
  - New Year's Eve, 1929-1963 (Box 213, Folder 7)
  - New York Academy of Medicine, 1937, 1940 (Box 213, Folder 8)
  - New York Academy of Sciences, 1959 (Box 213, Folder 9)
  - New York Adult Education Council
    - General, 1950 (Box 213, Folder 10)
    - Award to AHS, 1950 (Box 291, Folder 7)
  - New York Board of Rabbis, 1959 (Box 213, Folder 11)
  - New York Board of Trade, 1950, 1957-1964 (Box 213, Folder 12)
  - New York Central Railroad Co., 1954-1955 (Box 213, Folder 13)
  - New York Chamber of Commerce
  - New York City, 1948, 1952-1960 (Box 213, Folder 14)
    Includes AHS's statement for a promotional publication planned by the West Side Association of Commerce and related correspondence (1960), correspondence about plans to celebrate New York City's 300th anniversary in 1953 and a possible link with Columbia University's bicentennial (1952-1953), and Bernard Gimbel's letter praising Meyer Berger's articles about the city (1948).
  - New York City Anti-Crime Committee, 1951 (Box 213, Folder 15)
  - New York City Board of Education, 1954-1957 (Box 213, Folder 16)
  - New York City Cancer Committee, 1947-1961 (Box 213, Folder 17)
  - New York City Guide and Almanac, 1955 (Box 213, Folder 18)
  - New York Coliseum, 1954-1956, 1966 (Box 213, Folder 19)
  - New York County Medical Society
  - New York Daily News, 1946-1962 (Box 213, Folder 20)
  - New York Enquirer, 1952 (Box 213, Folder 21)
  - New York Express, undated (Box 213, Folder 22)
  - New York Financial Writers' Association, 1955 (Box 213, Folder 23)
  - New York Foundation, 1932-1963 (Box 214, Folder 1-4)
  - New York Foundling Hospital, 1955 (Box 214, Folder 5)
  - New York Heart Association, Inc., 1945-1961 (Box 214, Folder 6)
  - New York Herald Tribune
    These folders contain correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and other documents about the NYT's relations with its principal competitor, comparisons about news and editorial coverage, typography and design, circulation and promotion, and advertising volume and rates. They also include some personal correspondence between AHS and the Herald Tribune's owners and executives, and about their reciprocal support of each other's charities, the NYT's for the Fresh Air Fund, and the Herald Tribune's for the Hundred Neediest Cases. Included is correspondence about the merger with the World-Telegram & Sun and the Journal-American (1966), the Herald Tribune's agreement with route dealers (1962), Robert M. White's resignation as the president and editor of the Herald Tribune, charts of John H. Whitney's companies and investments, NYT's department heads' reports comparing the NYT's and the Herald Tribune's news coverage (1959-1960), letters, and clippings about Ogden Reid's resignation and White's appointment as president and editor of the Herald Tribune, E. C. Daniel's report comparing the use of photographs by the two papers, Turner Catledge's confidential report to OED on Whitney's plans for management of the Herald Tribune, papers about Whitney's financing plans (1958), memoranda and clippings about the Marie Torre case, involving the confidentiality of news sources, papers concerning Whitney's purchase of the Herald Tribune (1957), reports on the Herald Tribune's magazine sections and comparison to the NYT Magazine (1955-1956), letters and memoranda about the Herald Tribune's financial difficulties and rumors that the NYT was interested in acquiring it (1951-1954), a report on the Reid Foundation (1951), management changes at the Herald Tribune, its European edition and its arrangement with the European Recovery Administration for foreign aid funds (1948-1949), an analysis of Ogden Mills Reid's estate (1949), and memoranda on the Herald Tribune's alleged practice of lifting news from the NYT with examples (1927).
    - 1956-1966 (Box 214, Folder 7-11)
    - 1927-1955 (Box 215, Folder 1-5)
  - New York Historical Society
  - New York Hospital, 1959 (Box 215, Folder 6)
  - New York Journal-American, 1956-1957 (Box 215, Folder 7)
  - New York League for the Hard of Hearing
  - New York Mirror, 1955-1963 (Box 215, Folder 8)
  - New York Newspaper Women's Club, 1934-1967 (Box 215, Folder 9)
  - New York Philanthropic League, 1954 (Box 215, Folder 10)
  - New York Post, 1934-1962 (Box 215, Folder 11)
  - New York Press Association, 1955 (Box 215, Folder 12)
  - New York Public Library, 1923, 1945-1959 (Box 215, Folder 13-14)
  - New York School of Printing, 1956-1959 (Box 215, Folder 15)
  - New York School of Social Work, 1954-1961 (Box 215, Folder 16)
  - New York Southern Society, 1933-1934 (Box 215, Folder 17)
  - New York State Association of Chiefs of Police, 1955 (Box 215, Folder 18)
  - New York State Chamber of Commerce
  - New York State Council of Churches, 1956 (Box 215, Folder 19)
  - New York State Publishers Association, 1948, 1953, 1959 (Box 216, Folder 1)
  - New York State Reforestation Commission
  - New York State Society of Newspaper Editors, 1940, 1951 (Box 216, Folder 2)
  - New York Sun, 1943-1949 (Box 216, Folder 3)
  - New York Telegram, 1931 (Box 216, Folder 4)
  - New York Times Archives, 1955 (Box 216, Folder 5)
  - New York Times Building Co., 1965 (Box 216, Folder 6)
  - New York Times Co., Ltd.
  - New York Times Editions, 1956 (Box 216, Folder 7)
  - New York Times Emblem
  - New York Times Employees' Federal Credit Union, 1954-1958, 1964 (Box 216, Folder 8)
  - New York Times Employees Fund
  - New York Times Foundation, 1955-1967 (Box 216, Folder 9)
    Includes memoranda about its establishment, funding, administration, policy on grants, and rejection of some grant applications, reports, and meeting notices and minutes.
  - New York Times (France)
  - New York Times G. M. B. H.
  - New York Times Hall
  - New York Times Index, 1946-1968 (Box 216, Folder 10)
  - New York Times Magazine, 1933-1968 (Box 216, Folder 11-13)
    Includes memoranda by AHS offering suggestions, praise, and criticism, memoranda and reports about typography, use of color, advertising volume and rates, ratio of advertising to editorial matter, and increase in the magazines's size, AHS's memorandum about referring to the magazine by name, not just as another section (1937), and correspondence with Arthur Krock about paying staff members for contributions to the Magazine (1935).
  - New York Times Neediest Cases Fund
  - New York Times News Service, 1925-1968 (Box 216, Folder 14-16)